Guide to the Marvin Gettleman Papers TAM.523
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marvin Gettleman Papers
1976-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean
Gettleman, Marvin E.
Schrecker, Ellen
TAM.523
2.5 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes and 1 media box.
Marvin Gettleman (1933-2017) was an emeritus professor of history at the Polytechnic Institute of New York University. The collection reflects Gettleman's work as a historian, as well as with the New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean. The collection also contains audio materials collected by Gettleman on a range of topics related to the left. The New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean fought for human rights in Central America in the 1980s, with a focus on conditions in El Salvador and Guatemala. The group organized visits to the region and advocated for changes in United States foreign policy. The files contain reports, notes, newspaper and magazine clippings, correspondence, petitions, and research materials. There are newsletters, meeting minutes, and drafts of papers from an exchange between Gettleman and Harold Weissman. Audio materials in the collection contain recordings of interviews, debates, and lectures. Four interviews document the experiences of those effected by the Rapp-Coudert Committee of the early 1940s. Recordings of debates and lectures document the study of movements on the left in North America, Latin America, and Europe from 1976-2000.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marvin E. Gettleman in 2008; additional materials were donated by Marvin E. Gettleman and Ellen Schrecker in 2009, 2019, and 2020. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2009.095, 2019.039, 2020.009.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series:
Series I. New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean
Series II. Audio Materials
Series III. 2019 Accretion
Series IV. 2020 Accretion.
Files within Series I-II are arranged chronologically; accretions are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Marvin Gettleman (1933-2017) was an emeritus professor of history at the Polytechnic Institute of New York University. He was involved with many causes on the left, including the New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean in the 1980s.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains notes, clippings, articles, correspondence, and petitions documenting the activities of New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean and human rights in Latin America.
Newsletters, meeting minutes, and drafts of papers from an exchange between Marvin Gettleman and Harold Weissman document some of Gettleman's activities as a historian. FBI files from FOIA requests cover subjects that Ellen Schrecker and Marvin Gettleman researched together such as the Smith Act Trials, Kang Jai Association, Chinese Hand Laundry Alliance, Benjamin Mandel, and Clinton E. Jencks.
Audio materials in the collection contain recordings of interviews, debates, and lectures documenting the study of movements on the Left in North America, Latin America, and Europe from 1976-2000. Four interviews document the experiences of those effected by the Rapp-Coudert Committee of the early 1940s.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Guatemala -- Politics and government -- 20th century; United States -- Foreign Relations -- El Salvador; Human rights -- Guatemala.; El Salvador -- Politics and government -- 1979-1992.; United States -- Foreign Relations -- Guatemala; Human rights -- El Salvador; Newsletters.; Drafts (documents); Minutes (administrative records); Historians -- United States.; Research (document genres).; Communist Trial, New York, N.Y., 1952-1953; Faculty for Human Rights in El Salvador and Central America; Schrecker, Ellen; Weissman, Harold; Organization of American Historians; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate the Educational System of the State of New York
- Series I. New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean, 1977-1985; 470239
  Historical/Biographical Note
  The New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean was an organization focused on human rights and United States foreign policy in Central America in the 1980s. Their activities included the investigation of human rights abuses, lobbying the United States government, and organizing visits to El Salvador and Guatemala. The organization worked in cooperation with Faculty for Human Rights in El Salvador and Central America (FACHRES).
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains reports, notes, newspaper clippings, correspondence, articles, and petitions documenting the activities of New York Faculty Committee for Non-Intervention in Central America and the Caribbean and human rights in Latin America. The documents focus primarily on conditions in Guatemala and El Salvador. Notes and correspondence document members' visits to El Salvador and Guatemala. The series also contains research materials for writings on Central America, such as a photocopy of a special issue of Guatemalan Church in Exile titled "Guatemala, a New Way of Life: The Development Poles." Members corresponded with elected officials about United States foreign policy, and these materials are present. There are also documents from Faculty for Human Rights in El Salvador and Central America (FACHRES), the Peace Lobby, and other organizations.
  - 1977-1979, cuid33398; 270602 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1980, cuid33399; 334132 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1981, cuid33400; 270603 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1982, cuid33401; 470721 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1984, cuid33402; 470722 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1985, cuid33403; 470723 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Undated, cuid33404; 470724 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Slides: Nicaragua, El Salvador, 1983-1985; cuid33421 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II. Audio Materials, 1976-2000; 470240
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains recordings of interviews, debates, and lectures. Four interviews document the experiences of those effected by the Rapp-Coudert Committee of the early 1940s. Recordings of debates and lectures document the study of movements on the left in North America, Latin America, and Europe from 1976-2000.
  - E.P. Thompson at New York Socialist Conference, Feb 1976; cuid33405; 470243 (Box 2)
  - Karen Spaulding on history of Peru and Professor Woods, 1976; cuid33406; 470241 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Edward Rosen (Rapp-Coudert), 1977; cuid33407; 470250 (Box 2)
  - Dorothy Healy and Michael Harrington at ITT Forum, Jan 16, 1978; cuid33408; 470251 (Box 2, Cassette cuid33408A, cuid33408B)
  - Interview with Oscar Shaftel (Rapp-Coudert), 1978; cuid33409; 470247 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Sidney Shanker (Rapp-Coudert), 1978; cuid33410; 470248 (Box 2)
  - Music recorded in visit to Lutheran Refugio outside of San Salvador, 1985; cuid33411; 470252 (Box 2)
  - Mark Naison, "Thinking About American Communism," Brecht Forum, Sep 29, 1988; cuid33412; 470244 (Box 2)
  - World Historical Conference, Montreal Canada, 1995; cuid33413; 470254 (Box 2)
  - New York Marxist School, 1996; cuid33414; 470255 (Box 2)
  - Havard Debates on the origins of the New Left, Apr 17, 2000; cuid33415; 470253 (Box 2)
  - Sam Bowles on political economy at John Jay College, undated; cuid33416; 470249 (Box 2)
  - Marvin Gettleman, debates and lectures in Massachusetts, undated; cuid33417; 470245 (Box 2)
  - New York Marxist School [Brecht 3/10], undated; cuid33418; 470256 (Box 2)
  - Science and Society event featuring Eric Foner and Eleanor Leacock, undated; cuid33419; 470246 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Dudley Strauss (Rapp-Coudert), undated; cuid33420; 470242 (Box 2)
- Series III. 2019 Accretion, 1981-1982; 0.25 Linear Feet in 1 legal sized folder.
  Arrangement
  This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  This series contains newsletters and meeting minutes.
  - Newsletters, Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series IV. 2020 Accretion, 1978-1999; 1.5 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes.
  This accretion consists of FBI files requested by Ellen Schrecker and Marvin Gettleman through the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) during the 1990s. The FOIA requests primarily cover subjects such as the Smith Act Trials, Kang Jai Association, Chinese Hand Laundry Alliance, Benjamin Mandel, and Clinton E. Jencks.
  - Research Files, 1978, 1990, 1997; cuid33423 (Box 3, Folder 2-7)
  - Research Files, 1996-1999; cuid33424 (Box 4)
  - Research Files, 1979, 1981, 1996; cuid33425 (Box 5)